Open your phone right now
Yes, I am serious. Open your phone
After opening, either try opening
swiggy or Zomato
I will wait. Yeah, open it
So, after you open swiggy or Zomato
In real time, they are loading what
are all the nearby restaurants
And then, there are all the foods in
those restaurants
And the prices and the ratings that
the people has given to those foods
Isn't it? Every single thing loading
in your app in real time
Otherwise, swiggy or Zomato,
they don't own any of these
restaurants
Now, if they don't own these
restaurants, how do they know what
is being cooked in that restaurant,
in this kitchen, in this time?
Do you think it is magic?
No, it is not at all magic.
It is a one small technology which
is called API
It is a very important technology
Okay, so what is API?
API is Application Programming
Interface
So, using this API technology,
swiggy or Zomato or loading every
single thing in your app in real
time
So, by the end of this video,
you will understand what is API?
What is API? What is it used for?
When is it used? How is it used?
And not only that, how
can I build my own charge pt
application on my local machine
using just one charge pt API?
We will be able to do that
So, what is API?
Application Programming Interface
Just a fun fact, even these visuals
are made by cloud code
So, let's say you are building an
app and in that application,
you want to incorporate weather
information
If you want that weather
information, you can directly go and
build a satellite
So, there is some other company who
have already done that
So, what will you do?
So, you will go and ask the company,
let's say there is an open weather
company
They will go there and request for
the weather information and they
will put it in the app
And what that open weather company
will do is, it will send the data
back to you via a format called
API
And over the internet,
this communication is happening
Let's say you are building another
app and you want to use maps
So, if you want to use maps,
you can use a car and go around the
road and record the maps
Google has already done that
So, what you will do is,
you will go to Google and ask for
the maps
So, what Google will do is,
it will give you the details of the
maps via API
Maybe let's take one more example
You have to build a chart bot
To build a chart bot, you have to
spend 100 million dollars and train
a charge pt model
Because the charge pt has already
been done
Why do we need to spend 100s of
millions of dollars?
So, what will you do?
You will go to charge pt and charge
pt will send a question
Charge pt will process that question
and it will give you the answer back
via API
And then maybe let's take,
you want to make some payments
For that, you have built a bank,
right?
You will use something called as
Razorpay, Phonepay, Googlepay
All of these will support the
payments and even those will work
via APIs
And maybe let's take one more
example
You want to send emails
For that, you have built a world
wide web, right?
So, you use something which is
already built
So, what is API?
So, it's like an interface that you
can communicate with the third party
companies
That is what API is
So, let's look at the definition
An API is a doorway that lets your
app borrow another company's
capabilities over the internet
With a few lines of code
Very few lines of code
Maybe 10 lines max to max
You don't rebuild the world
You just ask what you need
That is what an API is
You might have a doubt in your mind
You are saying you will go and ask
the company
But how will you ask?
That is also important,
right?
And that is why we have something
called as request and response
For example, this is your local
machine
Maybe it can be a phone or laptop or
anything
Now, you are building an app
You need weather information in that
What you do is
Over the wifi, as you send a
WhatsApp message
You send a request to the company
Let's say open weather company
What they will ask is
I want to get today's weather
What will it do then?
It will validate that request
And it will send you the output
And then you will consume that
output in your application
To communicate like this
There is a package in python
And it's a very small and very easy
package
Which is called as request package
You can directly install it in
python
And within four lines of code
You can just get this request and
response
What are you doing first?
You are going to send a request
And this company is going to send
the response
And for that, you need an address,
right?
This company needs an address,
They will go there and ask
That address is this URL
HTTP API openweather.org weather
So using the python package called
request
And using the URL which is the
address
You will send a request
And from there, you will get the
response
And the response is the output that
you want
Very simple
Four lines of code
And all of this communication
Will happen in the format of JSON
JSON is basically a structured data
structure
Which can be used in Java,
Python, C, C++
Anywhere you can use this language
That is why all of this
communication is being done
Via JSON format
JSON format is very simple guys
It's like a dictionary
And if you don't know dictionaries
Please watch my video on the python
dictionaries
You will understand every single
thing
So like this, when you send a
request
You will get the output in the form
of JSON
We will learn more about this in the
later part of this video
So don't worry
Maybe let's say you want to build
your charge bit application
Locally
So what will you do?
Instead of openweather here
You will have OpenAI
OpenAI has this capability,
right?
So you will send your request to
OpenAI
And OpenAI will validate your
request
And send you the output
Simple
So at the end of the day
How do you send it?
You need to find where you want to
hit
This is my machine
Whether you want to hit to OpenAI
Whether you want to hit to GitHub
API
Or whether you want to get to
weather API
Every company has their own APIs
So you will go and ask
You will get the data
You will go and ask
That's how the request and response
works
via API in the format of JSON
It's good that you send it
Now there are many people in the
world
If everyone sends a request to
OpenAI or WeatherGun
Their servers will break,
right?
And who will get it?
So there should be something
Which should connect between you
securely
And that is what we call it as an
API key
What is API key?
You can think about it like a lock
to your house
If there is a lock in your house
Anyone can go to your house with
that lock
If they don't have a lock
They cannot enter your house,
right?
So what you do is
You go to OpenAI company
And you get registered
Register means
I want to communicate with you via
API
I want a key for that
Then OpenAI will provide a key for
you
So from next time
Whenever you are sending a request
Along with that request
You will send the key as well
So when you send a request to here
Along with the key
What OpenAI will do is
First it will validate
Whether the key is genuine or not
If the key is genuine
It will respond to your request
Otherwise it will not give the
response
So what happens because of this
Any company can control the number
of people
Who are sending these requests
And there is one more thing
You might be thinking of using a
chargpt
Maybe let's say
You pass a question like
What is a calculator?
So what should we do now?
This question will go to the chargpt
And chargpt will validate your key
And after that
Using a chargpt server
Using an intelligence
It will give you an answer
Maybe calculator is something
That you will want to do
The mathematical operations
And then
That response you are sending back
So here you are using the
capabilities
Of the company
Whether it is chargpt
Whether it is app
Whether it is github
So they are going to charge you
Some amount of money
Not every company will charge you
guys
At times chargpt will charge you
Some amount of money
Based on the number of requests
That you are doing
At times if you have github
Some github won't charge anything
So like that
Some companies have free APIs
Some companies have API keys
You will only get
Once you make the payments
What did you do?
You are sending a request
From your local machine
To the chargpt server
Or github server
You sent a request to some server
But did the request process
correctly or not?
Whether there are any issues or not?
How do you know?
So at times like that
We have these codes
Which are status codes
When you send a request
And when you get a response
You will get these status codes
Along with that response
In the form of JSON
Depending on these status codes
You can decide
Whether your request is a good
request
Or did you get a response or not?
If the status code is 200
The request you sent worked
There is also a response in the data
And then if the status code is 201
Something new was created
Common after post
Means you are sending some new data
And then 204
It worked
But we didn't get any response from
there
So if your status codes
Is in the form of 2xx
Which is 201 and 202
That means your request is getting
through
Maybe something happened
Sometimes you will get back
Sometimes you will not get back
But usually
You need to see request code as 200
That means you sent and got the
request code
So this is the first thing
And next
When you see the request codes
In the format of 4xx
That means it is going to be
something bad
Instead if you see the request code
as 400
That means in the request you sent
The data was not sent properly
It is in the wrong JSON
And 401 means
You have the API key
Maybe that API key is not valid
That is why we have the unauthorized
request
Because
There are API keys
That keys have a specific timeline
Maybe you have to work for one month
Maybe two months
Maybe three months
Maybe four months
Maybe a couple of days
Sometimes API will expire
That key will expire
Then you need to create a new key
So once your key is expired
Then if you use the same path key
If you send a request
You will get a code as unauthorized
And then maybe 403 is forbidden
And sometimes you get error code as
That means
The URL you sent
That URL or the address is wrong
You might have noticed it
When you don't have the internet
When you refresh
Error 404 will come
That is why this is
This is error 404
The URL is not working properly
And then there is 429
That means you are sending a lot of
requests
I will come to that point in a
minute
Which is called rate limiting
And then when you see some errors
Which are in the format of 5xx
That means
There is a server side problem
There is no problem on your side
When you see 500
Internal server issue
They are not working properly
And 502 is a bad gateway
And 503 means
The server is unavailable
Everything is fine as you send
But the server is not responding
So when you see 200 codes
That means everything is going good
When you see 400 codes
That means you are doing something
wrong
And when you see 500 codes
That means the server side is
something wrong
And then the next topic
Which is called rate limiting
What is this rate limiting
You have seen it before
You are sending from your laptop
You are sending to OpenAI
Let's say OpenAI
So like me
There are so many people
Who are going to send requests to
OpenAI
And every second
It needs to handle a lot of queries
But OpenAI is open to
every person in the world
So what do they do for that
They are going to limit you
Maybe per second
You put only 10 requests
So that this company needs to handle
to every other person
So they will put something called as
rate limiting
Each company will have something
like this
In the project I worked on
There is 1800 requests per second
So like this
Each company will have a rate
limiting
And we need to adhere to that rate
limiting policies
Otherwise
Maybe let's say
Let's say 10 requests per second
But you sent 11 requests
The 11th request will not process
Because RGPT cannot process more
than 10 requests per second
That is their limit
So whenever you are using any kind
of API
Always look at what is the rate
limiting
Let me do a reset
Now let's try
First it went OK
After that it cannot do
Because it will throw a 429 error
Which is too many requests
So these are all the basics
That everyone need to know about API
So let's summarize everything
API is an interface
That you can communicate between
companies via internet
In the form of JSON
So to hit an API request
You need a package called request
And in that you need an address with
URL
After that you can put the request
to any company
You will get the response
So to hit the response
You also need a key
Why the key?
Key is basically the gateway
That opens the door to the company
You need to put a key without anyone
doing it
And after that we have status codes
Whether the request you sent is
correct or not
Whether the server is working or not
To know all of these things
You will understand the server codes
And the next one is rate limiting
Such that the servers will be free
for everyone
And every company has their own rate
limiting
So we need to understand
How much rate limits are present for
every company
And we need to adhere to that
Now to understand all this
I created this IPython notebooks
Not.py files
If you don't know what IPython
notebooks are
I will link the video in the top
section here
You can go and watch it
You can use the same code in Google
collab as well
So if you don't have ES code
You can do it on there as well
So what we need to do is
First to talk to chargept
We will get an API key from the
machine
If you want a chargept API key
What we need to do is
We need to go to these links
And we need to sign up
So let me show you
See here
Go to the first link
You will get this one
And you go and log in with your
account
And look at here
API docs
You can look the API docs
If you want
There is another link here
This link if you open this one
You will get directly to this page
What we can do is
Once you logged in
You can create a secret key
What this means is
We are trying or asking the chargept
To create a key for us
For this we need to pay for it
Like credit card
We need to have some amount of money
To use chargept resources
If you don't have a credit card or
payment details
I will also show you a free
alternative
At the end of this video
So don't skip this part
So what we need to do is
We will create a new secret key
And I will say test secret key
Test key
And then default project
And I will give all the permissions
If you want
You can only give a little bit of
permissions as well
So that you don't have to use it
But let's not worry about that for
now
And I will create a secret key
And see
This is the key
That will be enabling us
To talk to the chargept
From our local machine
Once you generate this key
You need to copy it
Once you copy it
Just done
See here
Here the key came
So what I will do is
I will go to my VS code
Or cursor
Or any IDE
Here you need to save this key
securely
For that
I will create a file
Which is called an environment file
So maybe I will put it here
In this directory
I will put something like.env
.env means
It's an environment file
In this environment file
We will put all our keys
Why am I putting it here
If you know this key
You can even use this key
And you don't have to use it
I will get the bill
Once this video is public
I will delete the key
So that you can't use it
But to show it to you
I will put the key here
See
This is all a key
This is the key
That will enable us to talk to
charge party
But
When you put the key there
You need to save the key
Securely in a.env file
Step by step details
All are in the markdown file
You can look at it
So for that
I will just use this
OpenAI key equal to
And say
So what are we doing here
We can put multiple keys here
To say what that key is
We will say
OpenAI API key equal to
And say
We are keeping all of this key
We will save it here
We will save the file here
So now
Whenever you are writing your code
Here in the notebook
You will not copy paste the code
You will read the code
Directly from the environment file
Now to read in the environment file
You need a way
For that you need a package
Which is called.env
If you haven't installed these
packages
I highly recommend doing this step
PIP 3 install request package
Why request package
We are going to talk to the API
Via this API key
For that we need this request
package
And then
To read the file in our environment
We have this package called.env
And I will show you something
Which is called OpenAI
I will get to that point in a bit
And let's execute this
And I haven't set a kernel for this
yet
Let's say existing environments
And I will choose my virtual
environment
And it is going to connect to it
So that we can execute the code
And see
It is executing all of these things
Using cache memory
And installing the packages
It will install all the dependencies
What are we doing now
We are importing the OS
And from the package.env
We are calling this.env
Load.env
And we need to initialize this
You saw in the class
How to initialize a class
And after that
OS.getEnvironment
What does this mean
It is going to check
Any environment files
In those environment files
Here
It will check for this keyword
OpenAI API key
It also has the same thing
And make sure
When you are putting this API key
here
Let's not put any space
It will be just
Your key name
Equal to your key
That's it
And save it
And because of that
Now this package is able to read
this key
And then we are just printing
Key loaded
And we will not print this key here
Because we don't want to share the
key
With anyone else
Because if there is a key
Anyone can use it
And that billing will come to me
So I will not be doing that later on
After that
We got a nice key
Now we need a way
To talk to chargept
For that we have this
Request package
What we thought
Whenever we want to hit to an API
We need a URL
So this is the URL
You can find it in the API
documentation
See here
If you want
You can read these documentations
Usually that is good
And it is preferred actually
To read the documentation
But for now
I will not go through that
Because it will be
Like it will be a 2 hour video
So this is the URL that we want
And after that
We need to send our API key
Along with that URL
That is where we call it
As an authorization
This is called as headers
In authorization
You need to pass your key
Whatever your key is
And then you need to pass your
content type
Meaning you need to say
What is the method
What we thought in the beginning
All the communication between
The internet happens via
Format called JSON
What we are doing here
Content type application slash JSON
And in the body
We need to put a message
What we want to say with the charge
GPT
So this is the code here
Let me explain what is happening
here
See here
We have packaged the import request
And this is the URL
That we will use
To hit to the charge GPT
And then this is the header
Header means
This is where we will initialize
In a dictionary
Authorization
And we will put our API key here
In this place
Our API key will come
What is this SK hyphen
Something is there
That is what we are putting it here
In this format
And we are saying that
Content type application is done
That's all good
Now in charge GPT
There are different models
HGPT 4, HGPT 5, HGPT 5.5
Now we need to define
Which model we want to talk to
Because
Here is charge GPT
You will send a request
But which model you want to talk to
Even that needs to be specified
That is where you will say
You will declare everything in the
same body
You will create a dictionary
In that model
Which model you want to talk to
Which is GPT 4o mini
I want to use that
Why am I using this
This is a cheap model
You are talking
In every conversion
It is going to charge you money
So I don't want to use
GPT 5.5 high model
I don't want to get more billing
Because this is a demo purpose
If you want you can change this to
GPT 5.5
Do you have that documentation
You can find it in the
OpenAI documentation
I will put that link
In the description below as well
And then message
It is very important
First what you will do is
You will say role
That role is system
What are you telling the system
What are you telling
You are the helpful python tutor
Keep the replies under three lines
I don't want two big lines
Just wanted to see
Whether the API is working or not
After that role
User means you
This is what you are asking
What are you asking content
What is an API key
In one line
You can choose whatever you want
Hello, Hi, Where is
What are the famous places in
Hyderabad
You can put whatever you want
But this is the message
That you usually
Charging in the application
You talk a lot
That is what it is actually
What I am doing here
I will just put one line
What is an API key
And then
After all this
We need to send a request
That is what this line is
Request.post
You are sending it
What is with
You are sending url
What is my url
Along with that
What is my authorization tokens
This is my authorization token
And then
What is our body
We put the body in json
And then timeout
Remember
If you don't hit too much of time
It is going to break it
So that is why
We are keeping a timeout
And then we are printing a response
What is the code
Based on all of these things
You are going to
Connect from this local machine
To charge GPT servers
And after that
You are going to get a response
From charge GPT
Based on this authentication token
So execute this
And it is going to take some time
It took 2.2 seconds
And what is the response code
What is the response code 200
It is going through
And we got the output as well
But what is the output
That is where we have this
Response.status code
I can execute this piece of code
Means in response and json
We have something called as status
code
What is the status code
In output response.json
We have the output
Output will be in this
I will show you how to get this part
So just wait a minute
What is the reply here
An API key is a unique string of
characters
That grants access to an API
By identifying the user
Or application making the request
Means
We have given a question here
For this question
We got the answer here
Maybe let us try changing this
question
How to use Google collab
I have to use Google collab
And let us do this
And let us try to execute the same
thing again
And we are hitting the API one more
time
Every time when you want to send a
question
You are going to hit the API
And that is going to cost you some
amount of money
And what is the response code
200 again
Now let us see what is the output
now
Look
The response code is 200
To use the Google collab
Go to this collab website
www.collabreset.com and so on
And sign in with your Google account
And you can create your notebook
By choosing the file
New notebook
Or open an existing form of your
Google drive
And you can write and execute code
in the cells
And save your work directly to the
drive
So we are getting the answers
directly
From our local machine
You are not using charge jpt website
You are using the charge jpt models
But the output is coming via an API
through json
Hopefully it is clear
Now let us understand what is the
response clearly
So if you look at this one
This is what you will get as an
output
This is the full response json
So what is here
So first our id
What is this id
It is telling us that we are using a
charge completion API endpoint
And then this is what it is
And created when it was created
And whatever model we use
And then choices
Inside this we have the output
This is my output
So this entire thing is called a
json
In this json
Inside the choices
Inside the content
There is our response
And finish region stop
That means we have stopped naturally
And we have used many tokens
So what are these tokens
How much limit is there
What should we do
We will learn all of these things in
detail
Regarding the LLM phase
So for now let us not worry about
this
So this is the entire json
That is why what we have printed so
far
In response
In choices
We are printing content
That is how you are getting the
output as the
Charge GPT output
See here
In responses
In choices
In messages
We are printing content
Choices
Messages
Content
That is what the output that we are
going to get
So what are these fields
I have given the description here
Once the class is over
You can just read these things
And you will get more understanding
So all this is complex
Little bit
I mean this much of code writer
To hit an entire API
But other than all this
OpenAI company
They have their own package
Like Google has their own package
Lama has their own package
So like that
We can use their own packages
And the name of that package is
OpenAI
So from OpenAI
We are importing OpenAI
So till now we have kept all the
urls
Without keeping anything
You can just directly call
OpenAI
See here
We are calling the OpenAI package
And then you are giving your API key
What is our API key
And here
You are creating a client
Which is an instance of a class
And client dot
ChartCompletion
Dot create
I mean we are telling you to
complete the chart
And what is the model you want to
use
And the message we have kept till
now
You are putting it here
Nothing else
But url, authorization token,
header
So we don't need anything
And you will directly get the output
In this clean format
If you want
You can even use OpenAI packages
So see
You will get the same response
Not much difference actually
An API key is a unique identifier
Used to authenticate and authorize a
request
Made to an API
So
There will be questions in your
brain
Which one should you use
Should I use request package
Should I use OpenAI package
Actually if you are learning
Then I recommend using request
package
Because
You will understand every small
detail
On the APIs
If you already know these request
package
And everything
Then start using OpenAI
Because it is built by OpenAI
And if you can use request package
If you are calling multiple models
together
Maybe in your application
You want to call to ChargPT
And then you also want to call to
Gemini
You also want to call to Lama models
You also want to call to Grok
So if you want to call multiple
models
Instead of taking one package every
time
It is better if you use request
package
Because you just need to change the
token
That's it
So everything has its own pros and
cons
Based on the usage
You need to decide how to use it
If you don't have money
And you don't want to pay for
ChargPT
There are some open source models
So open source models means
You can use them for free of cost
And there are two ways
One is you can download the entire
model locally
And you need to have more power in
the local machine
To execute those models
Otherwise
There are some companies
Which will provide you for free of
cost APIs
For those open source models
And there are some limits obviously
Because you are using it for free
So there is a website which is
called as Grok
So GROQ
Okay
And we will go here
You also log in here
And we will put start building
And then did you see here
It has already logged in with my
account
So I will go here
And I will put API keys
Here you don't have to pay 20
No credit card, no debit card
Nothing else
Here also let's create an API key
And maybe let's say
API testing
I will name it
And I will put an expiry date of
7 days
It will expire in 7 days
And let's submit this key
Now it will also provide an
Key from the GROQ
Let's copy this
And done
Now GROQ came to us
Now where should we put the API key
You will also put this API key
Inside your environment
So go to the environment file
I will put it in the second line
Let's put it here
But it should have a name
So what is the name of it
I am putting it as GROQ API key
You can put whatever the name you
want
I will put it here
Equal to
Now in our environment file
We have GROQ API
So what we are going to do is
Now let's execute this piece of code
And see GROQ API is also loaded in
our notebook
Now if you go here
If you go to the playground
There are these LLMs here
You have all of these LLMs
Alibaba, Gwennan
And then Orpheus
GROQ has its own models
And also all the open source models
from the Meta
Lama 3.1
8 billion parameter model
Lama 3.3
70 billion parameter model
And you can use all of these
And from OpenAI
There are some open source models
You can even use these things as
well
So what we are going to do is
We will come here
And we will put the URL again
And then what is our authorization
type
What is the content type
And we will use Lama 3.3
70 billion versatile model
And if you are using GROQ
There are number of requests that
you can send per day
I think per day 1000 requests
Now see
Request package
Well advantage is
You are just changing the key
And you are just changing the URL
And then the model remaining
Everything is going to stay same
So I can execute this
And see I got this
An API key is a unique string of
characters
Used to authenticate and authorize
access
To specific application programming
interface
And we got the response
And it is much faster compared to
OpenAI as well
See
And tokens used 94
And cost 0.00
Because we didn't use any credit
card dealers
Or debit card details
So just like that
I said there is an application
called GROQ
With this website
They are hosting these LLMs for free
of cost
But this is also compatible with
OpenAI as well
So what can I do now
In OpenAI package
I can use API key
And change the URL here
It is not fun to change the URL in
the beginning
In OpenAI
Because it is by default from the
OpenAI
Now let's execute the same thing
And we get the output
See
Now you are using OpenAI package
You are hitting the GROQ server
You are not hitting the OpenAI
server
So like this
You can talk to any of these
companies
Via APIs using API key
And then if you want to try
different different models
What have we done here
I am trying different different
models
LAMA 3.370 billion
LAMA 3.18 billion
Gamma 2 9 bit
There are models called ITI
And we are creating a loop
In that loop
We are calling with different
different models
If you want to try
How the response looks like
With different different models
You get the output as well
Python is a great language
See Python simplicity readability
Depending on the model
The output is changing
Because of the intelligence of the
model
The output is changing
So when you are building
Production level applications
We need to decide
Which model works well for our
specific task
Claude will be good for some
Maybe charge GPT will be good for
some other specific tasks
So we need to decide
Which model works best for us
Based on how much costing it does
Because every response and every hit
It is going to cost us money
And this is a recap of what we have
learnt so far
If you have learnt something from
this video
Please let me know in the comment
section
And in the next video
We will also look at
What we can do it better
What have we done
We just hit an OpenAI server
And we got the response
But like our charge GPT
There is no conversation
There is no memory
Nothing at all
So how to build agents from this one
So it is just a basic information
So using this information
How you can expand this to build
agents
Multi -agent orchestration
State level management
There are many more topics
But this is the core of the topic
And if you are enjoying this video
Please subscribe
And share it with someone who needs
this
See you
Bye bye